A finding Aid to the Roy Moyer papers, 1923-2013, bulk dates 1950-2000, in the Archives of American Art AAA.moyeroy
Archives of American Art
Roy Moyer papers
bulk 1950-2000
1923-2013
AAA.moyeroy
Archives of American Art
2.7 Linear feet
The papers of artist and arts administrator Roy Moyer measure 2.7 linear feet and date from 1923 to 2013, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1950 to 2000. The materials also concern to a limited degree Moyer's life partner, artist and art historian, Karl Lunde. Moyer's career is documented by writings, photographs of his artwork and exhibiton installations, as well as printed materials concerning exhibitions and his participation in cutural and community activities. There is limited correspondence or material of a personal nature.
Moyer, Roy
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2011 by Karl Lunde.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Roy Moyer conducted by Paul Cummings in 1975.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1947-2008 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Letters, circa 1960s-1998 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 3: Writings, 1950-2007 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1950-2013 (Boxes 1-2; OV 5; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1959-2010 (Box 2; OV 5; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, 1950s-1970s (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1923-2000 (Boxes 2-4; OV 5; 0.7 linear feet)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of artist and arts administrator Roy Moyer measure 2.7 linear feet and date from 1923 to 2013, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1950 to 2000. The materials also conern to a limited degree Moyer's life partner, artist and art historian, Karl Lunde. Moyer's career is documented by writings, photographs of his artwork and exhibiton installations, as well as printed materials concerning exhibitions and his participation in cultural and community activities. There is limited correspondence or material of a personal nature.
Biographical materials consist of biographical sketches of Moyer, hand written lists of sold paintings and purchasers, Moyer's diploma from Columbia University (M.A.,1947), and a 1977 award from the National Academy of Design in New York. Scattered letters concern Moyer's exhibited paintings and his participation at art related conferences.
Subject files include multiple exhibitions at galleries, materials concerning Karl Lunde, Moyer's employment at the American Federation of Arts and UNICEF, and his contributions to book projects. Writings include an essay, short articles, and student papers.
Printed materials document Moyer's exhibition history and his participation as speaker or panelist at cultural events in the capacity of art critic or art historian. Some items mention Moyer as director of the American Federation of Arts in an endorsement capacity.
Original artwork by Moyer includes pencil drawings and a small sketchbook, including figures and still lifes in color. There are two drawings of unknown origin, one of Moyer and one which appears to be Moyer and Lunde together.
Photographs are of Moyer, Moyer with Lunde, their apartment, and Moyer with colleagues. Also found are photographs of Moyer's artwork and exhibition installations.
Biographical/Historical note
Artist and arts administrator Roy Moyer (1921-2007) and his life partner, artist and art historian Karl Lunde (1931-2009), lived and worked in the New York City area.
Moyer worked as the director of the American Federation of Arts for nine years, curating traveling art exhibitions, including the noted 50th anniversary re-creation of the 1913 New York Armory Show. During this period he also worked with art theorist Rudolph Arnheim on films relating to visual perception. Moyer then served as chief of art and design at UNICEF until 1986. He later devoted his time to painting and continued to exhibit until his death in 2007 following a hear attack.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
American Federation of Arts.; Lunde, Karl; UNICEF.; Art critics--New York (State)--New York; Art historians--New York (State)--New York; Arts administrators--New York (State)--New York; Drawings; Photographs
- Biographical Material, 1947-2008; Series 1; 1 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include seven biographical sketches of Moyer, one written for his memorial service at the Century Association in New York.
  - Biographical Material, 1947-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters, 1960s-1998; Series 2; 1 Folders Box 1
  There is a letter by Moyer to "AFA member(s)" that recommends the New York City Municipal Art Society tours. Also included are letters concerning Moyer's application to the Century Club. Letters received by Moyer acknowledge his artwork, generosity, or willingness to participate in exhibitions.
  - Letters, 1960s-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings, 1950-2007; Series 3; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Among Moyer's wriitngs are a draft entitled "Arts and Farces," a videocassette titled "Environmental Art: Working with the Elements," and a list of art and rare books in the Moyer and Lunde collection. Miscellaneous writings include varied topics such as "How to Price Art" and "On Life and Art." Student writings include papers about subjects of Antiquity, the Renaissance and a study of Picasso's Guernica written for Professor Meyer Schapiro. The list of collected art and rare books appears to have been written by Lunde.
  - "American Masters: Art Students League" Introduction, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Society of Contemporary Artists Newsletters, 2001-2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Arts and Farces", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Artspeak Articles, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Environmental Art: Working with the Elements", 1990; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of Collected Art and Rare Books, circa 1990-2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "New Directions for the Arts" Speech, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Student Writings, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Subject Files, 1950-2013; Series 4; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2; OV 5
  Subject files contain materials pertaining to exhibitions of Moyer's artwork in galleries such as The Contemporaries, Kendall and Battaglia Galleries, Keene Gallery, Midtown Gallery, and the Sneed Gallery. Files regarding Karl Lunde and his artwork are included in this series. Also found are Moyer's illustrations for a book by Vassilis Vassilikos, and images of horses and jockeys.
  - American Society of Contemporary Artists, 1985-2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Audubon Artists Exhibitions, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book Illustrations for Vassilis Vassilikos, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Federation of Arts, 2013; 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Butler Institute of American Art, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Child Study Association of America, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Contemporaries, 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dogangy Book, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Erika Weihs, 1991-2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Exhibitions "Aspects of Flowers" (1992), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Exhibitions at Kendall and Battaglia Galleries, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Exhibitions in Greece, 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Horses and Jockeys Images, undated; 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Illustrations for the Five Hundred Years Club, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Keene Gallery, 1992-1994; undated; Oversized material housed in OV 5 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Karl Lunde Miscellaneous, 1965-2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Karl Lunde Photographs of Paintings, 1955-1967; undated (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Midtown Galleries, 1961-1975; Oversized material housed in OV 5 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rockford, Illinois, circa 1970s; Includes 1 videocassette: U-matic (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Rolly-Michaux Gallery, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sara Roby Foundation Collection, 1971-1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sculpture on Shoreline Sites, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sneed Hillman/Sneed Gallery, 1969-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Society of the Four Arts 28th Annual Exhibition, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified Tape Recording, 1970s; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - United Nations, UNICEF Employment, 1971-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Keen Gallery and Midtown Galleries material from Box 2, Folder 2 and Box 2, Folder 6, 1993; 1967 (Box OV 5)
- Printed Material, 1959-2010; Seris 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2; OV 5
  Printed materials include reproductions of Moyer's artwork in magazines, pamphlets and materials that describe Moyer's participation as panelist or speaker at events, and ones that mention Moyer's endorsement as director of the American Federation of Arts. Also found is a William Doyle Auction Gallery catalog which includes artworks owned by Moyer and Karl Lunde sold with Lunde's estate.
  - Artwork by Moyer in Magazines, 1959-1975; Oversized material housed in OV 5 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Catalogs Mentioning Moyer, 1964-2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Doyle New York Auction Catalog-Karl Lunde Estate, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Materials, 1960-1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Catalogs, 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1961-1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Pamphlets Mentioning Moyer, 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Speaking Engagements or Panelist Participation, 1971-2005 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Oversized Artwork by Moyer in Magazines from Box 2, Folder 16, 1959-1975 (Box OV 5)
- Artwork, 1950s-1970s; Series 6; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Original drawings and works on paper in a small sketchbook constitute the main part of this series.
  - Sketchbook and Drawings by Moyer, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Drawings by Others, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Photographs, 1923-2000; Series 7; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-4; OV 5
  This series is mainly photographs of Moyer's paintings and drawings, but also includes some negatives and slides. Subjects are still lifes, figures, and landscapes. Also found are some photographs of Moyer in the course of professsional activities and in private life.
  - Apartment of Roy Moyer and Karl Lunde, circa 1990s-2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Artwork by Moyer in the Collection of William Peniston and George Robb, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Installations, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Paintings and Drawings, 1948-1990s (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Paintings and Drawings, 1948-1990s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Roy Moyer, 1923-circa 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Roy Moyer and Karl Lunde, 1950s-2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Roy Moyer with Colleagues, 1960s-1980s; Oversized material housed in OV 5 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sculpture by Moyer, 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Photographs of Moyer with Colleagues, from Box 4, Folder 4, 1960s (Box OV 5)